Now, I've been making pictures for quite a long time,
أمارس صناعة التصويرالفوتوجرافي منذ زمن زمن طويل
and normally speaking, a picture like this, for me,
وفي الاحوال العادية أقول أن صورة كهذه بالنسبة لي
should be straightforward.
لا بد ان تكون دقيقة.
I'm in southern Ethiopia. I'm with the Daasanach.
أنا في أثيوبيا مع أفراد من قيبلة الداسانك.
There's a big family, there's a very beautiful tree,
إنها عائلة كبيرة، وهناك شجرة جميلة كبيرة جداً
and I make these pictures with this very large,
وأنا أصنع صوراً بهذا الحجم الكبير
extremely cumbersome, very awkward technical plate film camera.
عملية مرهقة للغاية تتطلب استخدام نوع من الأفلام ذي تقنية صعبة
Does anybody know 4x5 and 10x8 sheets of film,
هل من أحد يعرف ذالك الفيلم بطبقات مقاساتها 4x5 و 10x8
and you're setting it up, putting it on the tripod.
تقوم بإعدادها أولاً قبل وضعها على الحامل ثلاثي القوائم .
I've got the family, spent the better part of a day talking with them.
حصلت على عائلة وقضيت أفضل أوقات النهار معهم.
They sort of understand what I'm on about.
قد فهموا نوعاً ما أريد فعله.
They think I'm a bit crazy, but that's another story.
ظنوا أني مصاب ببعض الجنون، هذه قصة اخرى عل أية حال.
And what's most important for me is the beauty and the aesthetic,
وما هو مهم لدي هو حسن الشيء وجمالياته
and that's based on the light.
وهذا يعتمد كله على الضوء.
So the light's setting on my left-hand side,
اتخذت وضعية بحيث توارى الضوء من جانبي الأيسر
and there's a balance in the communication with the Daasanach,
وهناك نوع من التوازن في التواصل مع الدسانك
the family of 30, all ages.
عائلة من 30 فرد من جميع الاعمار
There's babies and there's grandparents,
فهناك الرضع وهناك الأجداد
I'm getting them in the tree and waiting for the light to set,
انا أجمعهم إلى الشجرة منتظراً غروب الشمس
and it's going, going, and I've got one sheet of film left,
إنها تتوارى وتتوارى، بقيت طبقة واحدة من الفيلم
and I think, I'm okay, I'm in control, I'm in control.
أعتقد أني بحالة جيدة، أنا مسيطر، أنا مسيطر
I'm setting it up and I'm setting up, and the light's just about to go,
أعدها وأجهز نفسي والضوء أوشك على النزول
and I want it to be golden, I want it to be beautiful.
أريده ذهبياً، أريده جميلاً.
I want it to be hanging on the horizon so it lights these people,
أريده ان يتعلق بالأفق فيضيء هؤلاء الناس،
in all the potential glory that they could be presented.
حيث يمكن عرضهم بشكل متألق قدر الإمكان.
And it's about to go and it's about to go,
وهي توشك أن تذهب، توشك ان تذهب،
and I put my sheet in the camera,
ها أنا أغطي الكاميرا خاصتي
it's all focused,
كل قد تم تركيزه
and all of a sudden there's a massive "whack,"
وفجأة صدر صوت ضربة عنيفة
and I'm looking around, and in the top corner of the tree,
نظرت حولي وهناك في زاوية الشجرة في القمة
one of the girls slaps the girl next to her,
إحدى الفتيات تصفع الفتاة التي تجلس بجانبها
and the girl next to her pulls her hair, and all hell breaks loose,
وهذه شدت شعر تلك،فانحل كل شيء
and I'm standing there going, "But the light, the light.
أقف بمكاني هناك صارخاً "لكن الضوء، الضوء"
Wait, I need the light. Stay still! Stay still!"
انتظروا، أحتاج الضوء، ابقوا في أماكنكم!
And they start screaming,
وبدأوا بالصراخ،
and then one of the men turns around and starts screaming, shouting,
والتفت احد الرجال حوله وبدأ بالصراخ والعويل
and the whole tree collapses, not the tree, but the people in the tree.
فانهارت الشجرة كلها، ليست الشجرة نفسها، أقصد ما عليها من أشخاص.
They're all running around screaming, and they run back off into the village
جميعهم يحومون في دائرة، يصرخون، ومن ثم يتوارون داخل القرية.
in this sort of cloud of smoke, and I'm left there standing behind my tripod.
مخلفين ورائهم غيمة من الدخان، إنني واقفٌ في مكاني خلف حامل الكاميرا.
I've got my sheet, and the light's gone, and I can't make the picture.
أجمع أشيائي، ذهبت الشمس، ليس بإمكاني التقاط الصورة الآن.
Where have they all gone? I had no idea.
أين ذهب الجميع؟ لم يكن لدي أدنى فكرة.
It took me a week, it took me a week to make the picture which you see here today,
أخذت الامر مني أسبوعاً بأكمله لألتقط الصورة التي رأيتموها اليوم،
and I'll tell you why. (Applause)
وساخبركم ما السبب.
It's very, very, very simple -- I spent a week going around the village,
إنه بسيط للغاية فقد أمضيت أسبوعا بأكمله أحوم القرية
and I went to every single one: "Hello, can you meet at the tree?
ذهبت إلى كل شخص وقلت له: "مرحباً، هل يمكنك لقائي عند الشجرة؟"
What's your story? Who are you?"
"ما قصتك؟ من انت"
And it all turned out to be about a boyfriend, for crying out loud.
وعرفت فيما بعد أن ما حدث كان بسبب صديق احداهن لصراخه عالياً.
I mean, I have teenage kids. I should know.
أقصد، لدي أبناء مراهقين، وينبغي لي أن أعرف.
It was about a boyfriend. The girl on the top, she'd kissed the wrong boy,
كان بسبب صديق إحداهن، قامت الفتاة في القمة بتقبيل الولد الخطأ
and they'd started having a fight.
ومن هنا بدأ العراك.
And there was a very, very beautiful lesson for me in that:
وذلك كان بمثابة درس جميل جدا لي:
If I was going to photograph these people
فإذا أردت تصوير أولئك الناس
in the dignified, respectful way that I had intended,
بحيث يبدون بشكل محترم ووقور تماماً كما كنت أنوي آنذاك
and put them on a pedestal, I had to understand them.
وعرض صورتهم على جدارية، فكان ينبغي علي فهمهم أولاً.
It wasn't just about turning up. It wasn't just about shaking a hand.
لم يكن الامر مجرد حضور وتصافح بالأيدي.
It wasn't about just saying, "I'm Jimmy, I'm a photographer."
ولم يكن مجرد قول:" انا جيمي، انا مصور"
I had to get to know every single one of them,
كان ينبغي علي معرفة كل واحد منهم،
right down to whose boyfriend is who and who is allowed to kiss who.
بدءاً من قضية من صديق كل منهن، ومن يقبل من.
So in the end, a week later,
وهكذا في النهاية، بعد أسبوع،
and I was absolutely exhausted,
كنت مرهقاً للغاية
I mean on my knees going, "Please get back up in that tree.
أجثو على ركبتي قائلاَ: "أرجوكم ارجعوا لأعلى تلك الشجرة"
It's a picture I need to make."
"أريد إلتقاط صورة"
They all came back. I put them all back up in the tree.
رجعوا جميعهم هناك. وضعتهم جميعاً في الاعلى.
I made sure the girls were in the right position,
حرصت على وضع الفتيات في المكان الصحيح،
and the ones that slapped, one was over there.
أما اللاتي تبادلن الصفعات، احداهما كانت هناك
They did look at each other. If you look at it later,
يتبادلن النظرات، كما سترون لاحقاً
they're staring at each other very angrily,
يحملقن ببعضهم البعض بنظرات غاضبة
and I've got the tree and everything,
لدي الشجرة وكل شيء الآن.
and then at the last minute, I go, "The goat, the goat!
وبعدها وفي آخر لحظة ، سابدأ، "الماعز، الماعز!"
I need something for the eye to look at. I need a white goat in the middle."
أريد شيئاً لتراه الاعين. أريد ماعزاً أبيض في الوسط"
So I swapped all the goats around. I put the goats in.
قايضت جميع الماعز هناك، ووضعتها بالوسط.
But even then I got it wrong, because if you can see on the left-hand side,
تبين لي بعدها انني اخترت الماعز الخطأ، انظر الى الجانب الايسر
another little boy storms off because I didn't choose his goat.
استشاط أحدهم غضباً لانني لم اختر ماعزه.
So the moral being I have to learn to speak Goat as well as Daasanach.
فكان الدرس آنذاك أن أتعلم كيفية التحدث مع الماعز كالتحدث الى الداسانك
But anyway, the effort that goes into that picture
وعلى أية حال فالجهد الذي بذلته على تلك الصورة
and the story that I've just related to you,
والقصة التي رويتها لكم
as you can imagine,
كما تصورتموها
there are hundreds of other bizarre, eccentric stories
هنالك المئات من القصص الغريبة والعجيبة
of hundreds of other people around the world.
لمئات من البشر حول العالم.
And this was about four years ago, and I set off on a journey,
كان هذا قبل أربع سنوات، حينها أنطلقت في رحلة
to be honest, a very indulgent journey.
ولأكون صادقاص، كانت رحلة للتحرر.
I'm a real romantic. I'm an idealist, perhaps in some ways naive.
أنني شخص حقاص رومانسي ومثاليٌ أيضا وربما ساذج بشكل أو بآخر أحياناً.
But I truly believe that there are people on the planet that are beautiful.
ولكنني حقيقة أؤمن بوجود أشخاص جميليين على هذا الكوكب.
It's very, very simple. It's not rocket science.
أنها بغاية البساطة، ليست علم الصواريخ.
I wanted to put these people on a pedestal.
أردت وضع هؤلاء الناس على جدارية.
I wanted to put them on a pedestal like they'd never been seen before.
أردت وضعهم على جدارية وكأن لم يرهم أحد من قبل.
So, I chose about 35 different groups,
ولذلك اخترت خمس وثلاثين مجموعة مختلفة.
tribes, indigenous cultures.
وقبائل وثقافات أصلية.
They were chosen purely because of their aesthetic,
تم انتقاؤهم بعفوية بسب جمالياتهم
and I'll talk more about that later.
وسأتحدث عن ذلك لاحقاً.
I'm not an anthropologist, I have no technical study with the subject,
أنا لست متخصصا في الانثروبولوجي وليس لدي دراسة فنية به.
but I do have a very, very, very deep passion,
ولكن لدي شغف عميق جدا
and I believe that I had to choose the most beautiful people on the planet
واعتقد أن لا بد لي من أختيار أجمل الناس على هذا الكوكب.
in the most beautiful environment that they lived in,
في اجمل بيئة عاشوا فيها،
and put the two together and present them to you.
دمج الاثنين مع بعضهما وتقديمهم لكم.
About a year ago,
قبل سنة مضت
I published the first pictures,
نشرت اول صوري
and something extraordinarily exciting happened.
حدث أمر بغاية الاثارة
The whole world came running,
فجاء العالم كله راكضاً
and it was a bizarre experience, because everybody, from everywhere:
لقد كانت تجربة غريبة، ردد الجميع من كل مكان
"Who are they? What are they? How many are they?
من هم؟ ماهيتهم؟ كم عددهم؟
Where did you find them? Are they real? You faked it.
أين وجدتهم؟ هل هم حقيقة أم زيف؟
Tell me. Tell me. Tell me. Tell me." Millions of questions for which,
أخبرني، أخبرني، أخبرني ، اخبرني" ملايين الأسئلة التي
to be honest, I don't have the answers.
لم اجد لها أجوبة بصراحة.
I really didn't have the answers,
لم اعرف حقاص الاجوبة،
and I could sort of understand, okay, they're beautiful, that was my intention,
كان بإمكاني فهم جمالهم نوعاً فقد كانوا كذلك وهذا ما كنت انويه
but the questions that I was being fired at,
لكن الاسئلة التي وجهت الي كوابل من الرصاص
I could not answer them.
لم يكن بإمكاني الاجابة عليها.
Until, it was quite amusing, about a year ago
هكذا حتى السنة الماضية، وقد كان الامر ممتعاً.
somebody said, "You've been invited to do a TED Talk."
قال لي احدهم، "تم دعوتك لان تقدم محاضرة لتيد"
And I said, "Ted? Ted? Who's Ted? I haven't met Ted before."
فقلت متسائلاً،"تيد؟ تيد؟ من هو تيد؟ لم أقابل تيد من قبل
He said, "No, a TED Talk." I said, "But who's Ted?
فقال لي:"لا، انها محاضرة في تيد" فقلت،"من هو تيد؟"
Do I have to talk to him or do we sit with each other on the stage?"
هل ينبغي علي ان اتكلم معه أو نجلس معاً على المسرح؟"
And, "No, no, the TED group. You must know about it."
فقال لي:"لا، لا ، مجموعة تيد. لا بد أنك تعرف شيئاً عنها"
And I said, "I've been in a teepee and in a yurt for the last five years.
فقلت:"امضيت حياتي في الخيام السنوات الخمس الأخيرة"
How do I know who Ted is? Introduce me to him."
"فكيف لي أن اعرف من هو تيد؟" قدمني له.
Anyway, to cut a long story short, he said, "We have to do a TED Talk."
على أية حال، اختصارا للحديث، قال :"يجب ان نقوم بالقاء محاضرة في تيد"
Researched. Oh, exciting. That's great!
قمت بالبحث. إنه لشيء مثير. ذلك عظيم!
And then eventually you're going to go to TEDGlobal.
واخيراً ستذهب الى مجموعة تيد العالمية.
Even more exciting.
وذلك أكثر متعة.
But what you need to do, you need to teach the people lessons,
لكن ما تحتاج الى القيام به هو ان تقوم بتعليم الناس دروساً
lessons that you've learned on your travels around the world
الدروس التي تعلمتها في أسفارك حول العالم
with these tribes.
مع تلك القبائل.
I thought, lessons, okay, well, what did I learn? Good question.
فكرت، دروس، حسناً، ماذا تعلمت. سؤال جيد.
Three. You need three lessons, and they need to be terribly profound.
ثلاثة. تحتاج الى دروس ثلاثة. يريدونها ذات عمق.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And I thought, three lessons, well, I'm going to think about it.
ففكرت، ثلاثة دروس، حسناص، سأفكر بذلك.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
So I thought long and hard, and I stood here two days ago,
لذا فكرت ملياً وبجد، ووقفت هنا قبل يومين،
and I had my test run, and I had my cards
وبدأ إختباري، ولدي بطاقاتي
and my clicker in my hands and my pictures were on the screen,
وجهاز التحكم بيدي، وصوري على الشاشة،
and I had my three lessons, and I started presenting them,
ولدي دروسي الثلاثة، وبدأت بتقديميهم،
and I had this very odd out-of-body experience.
فأحسست بغرابة التجربة وكأنني كنت منفصلاً عن جسدي.
I sort of looked at myself standing there, going, "Oh, Jimmy,
فنظرت لنفسي واقفاً هناك مخاطباً: "أوه، جيمي"
this is complete loads of codswallop.
إن هذا كله هراء
All these people sitting here, they've had more of these talks,
فلدى كل من الحاضرين الكثير من هذه الاحاديث
they've heard more lessons in their life.
سمعوا عن دروس أكثر في حياتهم.
Who are you to tell them what you've learned?
من انت لتقل لهم ماذا تعلمت؟
Who are you to guide them and who are you to show them
من انت لترشدهم وتبين لهم
what is right, what is wrong, what these people have to say?"
ما هو الصحيح وما هو الخاطئ، ماذا سيقوله أولئك الناس عندها؟
And I had a little bit of a, it was very private,
فاحسست بشيء من، وهذا أمر شخصي،
a little bit of a meltdown.
أحسست بقليل من بالانهيار.
I went back, and a little bit like the boy walking away from the tree with his goats,
فرجعت، كطفل صغير ابتعد عن الشجرة هو وماعزه
very disgruntled, going, that didn't work,
مستاءاً ومردداً في نفسي أن هذا لن ينجح،
It wasn't what I wanted to communicate.
فلم يكن ذلك ما أردت إيصاله للناس.
And I thought long and hard about it, and I thought, well, the only thing
فكرت ملياً وبجدية حيال الامر وفكرت، حسناً الشيء الوحيد
I can communicate is very, very basic.
الذي يمكن إيصاله لهم أساسي للغاية.
You have to turn it all the way around.
لا بد لي من أغير هذا كله.
There's only one person I know here, and that's me.
هناك شخص واحد فقط اعرفه، ألا وهو انا.
I'm still getting to know myself,
ينبغي أن اعرف نفسي أكثر.
and it's a lifelong journey, and I probably won't have all the answers,
إنها رحلة عمر بأكمله،ومن الممكن أن لا أحمل الاجوبة على الأسئلة جميعها،
but I did learn some extraordinary things on this journey.
لكنني تعلمت أموراً عجيبة في رحلتي هذه.
So what I'm going to do is share with you my lessons.
وما سأقوم به الىن هو مشاركتكم بدروسي.
It's a very, as I explained at the beginning, very indulgent, very personal,
وانها -كما قلت لكم منذ البداية- ذات عمق وخصوصية كبيرة
how and why I made these pictures,
كيف ولماذا التقطت هذه الصور،
and I leave it to you as the audience to interpret what these lessons
وسأتركها لكم أنتم الجمهور لتفسرون ماذا هذه الدروس
have meant to me, what they could perhaps mean to you.
عنت لي، وماذا قد تعني لكم أنتم.
I traveled enormously as a child.
سافرت كثيراً كما الطفل.
I was very nomadic. It was actually very exciting.
كنت رحالاً بدائياً بالفعل.
All around the world,
حول العالم
and I had this feeling that I was pushed off at great speed
وشعرت بأنني قد انجرفت بسرعة
to become somebody, become that individual, Jimmy.
لأتحول لشخص ما، لأصبح فرداً، هو جيمي.
Go off into the planet, and so I ran, and I ran,
وشردت في هذا الكوكب ولذلك ركضت، واصلت الركض.
and my wife sometimes kids me, "Jimmy, you look a bit like Forrest Gump,"
تمازحني زوجتي أحياناً، "جيمي، تشبه فورست جامب قليلا"
but I'm, "No, it's all about something, trust me."
لكنني،"لا ، إن هذا كله يرجع الى شيء ما، ثقي بي".
So I kept running and I kept running, and I sort of got somewhere
لذلك واصلت الركض، واصلت الركض. فوصلت الى مكان ما نوعا ما.
and I sort of stood there and looked around me and I thought, well,
فوقفت ونظرت من حولي وفكرت، حسناً،
where do I belong? Where do I fit?
إلى أين أنتمي؟ أين أجد نفسي؟
What am I? Where am I from? I had no idea.
ما أنا؟ من أين جئت؟ لم يكن لدي أدنى فكرة.
So I hope there aren't too many psychologists in this audience.
ولذلك آمل ان لا يكون أخصائيون نفسيون في الجمهور.
Perhaps part of this journey
ربما جزء من هذه الرحلة
is about me trying to find out where I belonged.
هدفه محاولة البحث عن المكان الذي انتمي اليه.
So whilst going, and don't worry, I didn't when I arrived with these tribes,
ولذا بينما أنا ذاهب، لا تقلقوا، لم أقم لدى وصولي عند هذه القبائل
I didn't paint myself yellow and run around with these spears and loincloths.
لم أقم بدهن نفسي باللون الاصفر ولم احوم حاملاً الرماح وجلد الأسود.
But what I did find were people that belonged themselves,
ولكن ما وجدته كان أناساً ينتمون لأنفسهم،
and they inspired me, some extraordinary people,
وقد ألهموني، كانوا أشخاصاً مميزين حقاً،
and I'd like to introduce you to some heroes of mine.
وأرغب أن أقدم لكم بعض أبطالي.
They're the Huli.
انهم رجال قبيلة الهولي.
Now, the Huli are some of the most extraordinarily beautiful people
والان، الهولي هم من أكثر البشر جمالاً
on the planet.
على هذا الكوكب.
They're proud. They live in the Papua New Guinean highlands.
فخورين بانفسهم. يقطنون تلال بابو الجديدة في غينيا.
There's not many of them left, and they're called the Huli wigmen.
لم يتبقى الكثير منهم، يطلقون عليهم اسم رجال "الباروكات"
And images like this, I mean, this is what it's all about for me.
وصور كهذه ، أقصد، إنها ما أريد ان أقوله.
And you've spent weeks and months there talking with them, getting there,
أمضيتم أسابيعاً وأشهراً تتحدث إليهم، تذهب هناك،
and I want to put them on a pedestal, and I said, "You have something
وأردت أن اعلق صورتهم كجدارية وقلت" تملكون شيئاً
that many people have not seen.
لم يره الآخرون من قبل.
You sit in this stunning nature."
تجلسون في هذه الطبيعة الخلابة"
And it really does look like this, and they really do look like this.
إنها تبدو هكذا فعلاً، وهم كذلك أيضاً يبدون كما هم حقيقة.
This is the real thing.
إن هذا شيء حقيقي.
And you know why they're proud? You know why they look like this,
وهل تعرفون لما هم فخورين بأنفسهم؟ هل تعرفون لما يبدون بهذا الشكل
and why I broke my back literally
ولما كسرت ظهري حقيقة
to photograph them and present them to you?
لتصويرهم وتقديمهم اليكم؟
It's because they have these extraordinary rituals.
السبب وراء ذلك يكمن في طقوسهم العجيبة
And the Huli have this ritual: When they're teenagers,
يمارسون هذا الطقس، من أن يصلوا مرحلة المراهقة
becoming a man, they have to shave their heads,
حتى يصبحون رجالاً، لا بد أن يحلقوا رؤوسهم كل يوم،
and they spend the rest of their life shaving their heads every single day,
ويمضون بقية حياتهم يحلقون رؤوسهم كل يوم
and what they do with that hair,
وما يفعلون بذلك الشعر،
they make it into a creation,
إنهم يحولونه الى شيء في غاية الإبداع
a creation that's a very personal creation.
ذلك الإبداع الذي يعكس الذات
It's their creation. It's their Huli creation.
إنه إبداع منهم. إنه إبداع الهولي.
So they're called the Huli wigmen.
ولذلك يسمونهم رجال الهولي ذوي الباروكات
That's a wig on his head.
أنه يعتلي باروكة.
It's all made out of his human hair.
وهي مصنوعة من الشعر البشري.
And then they decorate that wig with the feathers of the birds of paradise,
وبعد ذلك يزينون تلك الباروكات بريش طيور الجنة
and don't worry, there are many birds there.
لا تقلقوا، هنالك الكثير من هذه الطيور.
There's very few people living, so nothing to get too upset about,
لم يتبقى منهم سوى ما ندر، لذل ليس هنالك ما يدعو للقلق بشأنه،
and they spend the rest of their life recreating these hats
ويمضون بقية حياتهم يعيدون تكوين هذه القبعات
and getting further and further,
ويستمرون بذلك أكثر فأكثر
and it's extraordinary, and there's another group,
أنه شيء مميز، وهنالك مجموعة اخرى،
they're called the Kalam, and they live in the next valley,
ويسمون الكالنج ويعيشون في الوادي المجاور
but they speak a completely different language,
ولكنهم يتحدثون بلغة مختلفة تماماً،
they look completely different, and they wear a hat,
وأشكالهم أيضاً مختلفة كلياً ويعتلون القبعات
and it's built out of scarabs,
وهي مصنوعة من الجعارين
these fantastic emerald green little scarabs,
الجعارين الصغيرة ذات اللون الأخضر الزمردي،
and sometimes there are 5,000 or 6,000 scarabs in this hat,
تجد ما يقارب الخمسة أو الستة الالاف من تلك الجعارين على القبعة
and they spend the whole of their life collecting these scarabs
يمضون حياتهم بطولها في جمع تلك الجعارين
to build these hats.
لصنع تلك القبعات.
So the Huli inspired me in that they belong.
لقد الهمني رجال الهولي بما ينتمون إليه.
Perhaps I have to work harder at finding a ritual which matters for me
لربما ينبغي على العمل بجد أكثر لإيجاد الطقس الذي يهمني
and going back into my past to see where I actually fit.
والرجوع الي ماضيي لأرى أين أنتمي فعلاً.
An extremely important part of this project
جزء مهم جدا من هذا المشروع
was about how I photograph these extraordinary people.
كان إيجاد كيفية تصوير أولئك الأشخاص المميزين.
And it's basically beauty. I think beauty matters.
تكمن ببساطة في الجمال. أعتقد أن الجمال ما يهم حقأً.
We spend the whole of our existence revolving around beauty:
نمضي طيلة حياتنا نسعى وراء ما هو جميل:
beautiful places, beautiful things, and ultimately, beautiful people.
الاماكن الجميلة والأشياء الجميلة والأشخاص الجميليين بشكل أساسي.
It's very, very, very significant.
أنه أمر بغاية الاهمية.
I've spent all of my life analyzing what do I look like?
أمضيت حياتي أحلل في ما أشبه أنا
Am I perceived as beautiful?
هل أنا جميل؟
Does it matter if I'm a beautiful person or not,
هل يهم فيما اذا كنت شخصاً جميلا أم لا،
or is it purely based on my aesthetic?
أم انه امر مبني على جمالياتي؟
And then when I went off, I came to a very narrow conclusion.
وعندما انتهيت من تفكيري وصلت الى استنتاج بغاية الدقة.
Do I have to go around the world photographing, excuse me,
هل أحتاج لرحلة حول العالم والتقاط الصور: عذراً،
women between the age of 25 and 30? Is that what beauty is going to be?
النساء اللاتي اعمارهن ما بين 25 و30؟ هل هذا هو الجمال؟
Is everything before and after that utterly irrelevant?
هل كل شيء -ما كان وما سيكون- غير مضمن في المعادلة؟
And it was only until I went on a journey,
لم أجد جواباً حتى ذهبت في رحلة،
a journey that was so extreme,
رحلة متطرفة للغاية،
I still get shivers when I think about it.
لا زلت أرتعش بمجرد التفكير بها.
I went to a part of the world, and I don't know whether any of you
ذهبت الى جزء من العالم، لست أعلم إن كان أحدكم
have ever heard of Chukotka. Has anybody ever heard of Chukotka?
قد سمع بشكوتكا. هلم منكم من سمع بشكوتكا؟
Chukotka probably is, technically, as far as one can go
تقنياً قد تكون شكوتكا هي أقصى نقطة يمكنك الذهاب اليه
and still be on the living planet.
وما زالت مكاناً للعيش على هذا الكوكب.
It's 13 hours' flight from Moscow.
تبعد مسافة ثلاثة عشرة ساعة عن موسكو.
First you've got to get to Moscow, and then 13 hours' flight nonstop from Moscow.
لا بد أن تصل موسكو اولاً، ومن ثم الاقلاع ثلاثة عشرة ساعة دون توقف
And that's if you get there.
ذلك كله لتصل هناك.
As you can see, some people sort of miss the runway.
وكما ترون، البعض قد يضيع الطريق للمدرج.
And then when you land there, in Chukotka are the Chukchis.
وعند الهبوط هناك في شكوتكا تجد جماعة الشوكتشيز
Now, the Chukchis are the last indigenous Inuits of Siberia,
والشوكتشيز هم آخر جماعات الانويت الأصليين في سيبيريا
and they're people I'd heard about, I'd hardly seen any images of,
وهم أشخاص كنت قد سمعت بهم، ولكنني لم أرى بحياتي صوراً لهم،
but I knew they were there,
لكنني عرفت أنهم هناك،
and I'd been in touch with this guide,
كنت على توصل مع ذلك المرشد،
and this guide said,
قال لي ذلك المرشد،
"There's this fantastic tribe. There's only about 40 of them.
هناك تقطن تلك الفبيلة الرائعة. تبقى منهم أربعون.
You'll be okay. We'll find them." So off we went on this journey.
"ستكون بخير. سنجدهم" وانصرفنا لرحلتنا.
When we arrived there, after a month of traveling across the ice,
ولدى وصولنا هناك، بعد شهر من السفر عبر الجليد،
and we'd got to them, but then I was not allowed to photograph them.
وصلنا إليهم، ولكن بعدها لم يسمحول لي بتصويرهم.
They said, "You cannot photograph us. You have to wait.
قالوا:"لن تتمكن من تصويرنا. يجب أن تنتظر"
You have to wait until you get to know us. You have to wait until you understand us.
يجب أن تتريث حتى تعرفنا. يجب أن تتريث حتى تفهمنا.
You have to wait until you see how we interact with one another."
يجب ان تتريث حتى ترى كيف نحتك ببعضنا البعض
And only then, it was many, many weeks later, I saw a respect.
بعدها فقط ، كانت مدة طويلة، أسابيع عدة بعدها، وجدت الاحترام.
They had zero judgment.
لم يصدروا احكاماً علي.
They observed one another, from the youth, from the middle aged to the old.
انتبهوا لبعضهم سواء من الشباب ومن الكهول ومن العجائز.
They need each other.
احتاجوا لبعضهم البعض.
The children need to chew the meat all day
ينبغي للأطفال مضغ اللحم طوال اليوم
because the adults don't have any teeth,
لأن البالغين ليس لديهم الأسنان لفعل ذلك،
but at the same time, the children take the old aged people out
وفي نفس الوقت يرافق الأطفال كبار السن للخارج
to the toilet because they're infirm,
حيث المرحاض بسبب عجزهم.
so there's this fantastic community of respect.
إن هذا مجتمع رائع مبني على الاحترام.
And they adore and admire one another, and they truly taught me
وهم يحبون ويحترمون بعضهم البعض، وقد علموني حقاً
what beauty was.
ما هو الجمال؟
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Now I'm going to ask for a little bit of audience interaction.
سأطلب قليلاً من التفاعل من الجمهور.
This is extremely important for the end of my talk.
هذا مهم جداً لإنهاء حديثي.
If you could look at somebody left to the right of you,
اذا كان بإمكانك النظر لشخص بجانبك،
and I want you to observe them,
وأردتكم ان تنظروا اليهم،
and I want you to give them a compliment. This is very important.
أريدكم ان تمدحوهم. هذا مهم جداً.
Now, it may be their nose or their hair or even their aura, I don't mind,
قد يكون شيئاً مميزا في أنوفهم أو شعرهم أو حضورهم
but please look at each other, give them a compliment.
أرجوكم أنظروا الى من جانبكم، أمدحوهم.
You have to be quick, because I'm running out of time.
أسرعوا أرجوكم،فوقتي ينفذ.
And you have to remember it.
يجب ان تتذكروا ذلك.
Okay, thank you, thank you, thank you, you've given each other compliments.
حسنا شكرا شكرا، قمتم بمدح بعضكم البعض.
Hold that compliment very, very tightly. Hold it for later.
تمسكوا بهذا المديح جيداً. تمسكوا به لوقت لاحق
And the last thing, it was extraordinarily profound,
وآخر أمر كان عميقا بشكل لا يعقل،
and it happened only two weeks ago. Two weeks ago I went back to the Himba.
حدث قبل أسوعين فقط. قبل أسبوعين رجعت الى قبيلة هيمبا.
Now, the Himba live in northern Namibia on the border of Angola,
تعيش قبيلة هيمبا في شمال ناميبيا على حدودها مع أنغولا.
and I'd been there a few times before,
كنت قد تواجد هناك عدة مرات من قبل،
and I'd gone back to present this book I'd made,
رجعت لأقدم كتاباً كنت قد أنجزته،
to show them the pictures, to get into a discussion with them,
لأريهم الصور، ولأدمجهم بنقاش معي،
to say, "This is how I saw you. This is how I love you.
لأقول:"هكذا رأيتكم. هكذا أحبكم.
This is how I respect you. What do you think? Am I right? Am I wrong?"
هكذا أحترمكم. ماذا تعتقدون؟ هل أن على محق؟ أم مخطىء؟"
So I wanted this debate. It was very, very, very emotional,
أردت الخوض في هذا الجدل. لقد كان بالفعل جياشاً بالعاطفة.
and one night we were sitting around the campfire,
في إحدى الليالي كنا جالسين حول نار المخيم،
and I have to be honest, I think I'd had a little bit too much to drink,
وينبغي أن اكون صادقاً، أعتقد أنني أسرفت بالشرب ليلتها،
and I was sort of sitting under the stars going, "This is great,
جلست تحت النجوم قائلاً: "إن هذا شيء عظيم
you've seen my pictures, we love each other." (Laughter)
لقد رأيتم صوري، نحن نحب بعضنا البعض" (ضحكات)
And I'm a little bit slow,
أنا بطيء بعض الشيء،
and I looked around me, and I said,
نظرت حولي وقلت:
I thought, maybe, the fence is missing.
فكرت لربما لا يوجد سياج.
Wasn't there a fence here last time I came?
ألم يكن هناك سياج من قبل؟
You know, this big protective fence around the village,
كما تعلمون فهذا السياج الكبير يحمي أطراف القرية
and they sort of looked at me and go, "Yeah, chief die."
اخدت بالنظر لنفسي وقلت: " نعم، لقد مات الزعيم"
And I thought, okay, chief dying, right, you know,
وفكرت. حسنا. بموت الزعيم، انتم تعرفون
look up at the stars again, look at the campfire.
وجهت ببصري للاعلى للنجوم ثانية ثم نظرت لنار المخيم
Chief die. What on Earth does chief die have to do with the fence?
فإذا مات الزعيم، بحق الله، ما دخل السياج بذلك؟
"Chief die.
"مات الزعيم."
First we destroy, yeah? Then we reflect.
أولاً نهدم، أليس كذلك؟ ثم نتفكر.
Then we rebuild. Then we respect."
ثم نعيد بناءه. ثم نحترم."
And I burst out in tears, because my father had only just died
فانفجرت بعدها بالبكاء لأن والدي كان قد توفى بوقت قريب.
prior to this journey,
قبل الرحلة هذه
and I didn't ever acknowledge him,
ولم أشكره قط
I didn't ever appreciate him for the fact that I'm probably standing here today
لم أقدر أنه كان السبب لربما في وقوفي هنا اليوم
because of him.
كل هذا بسببه.
These people taught me that we are only who we are because of our parents
علمني هؤلاء الأشخاص ان ما نحن عليه هو بسبب آبائنا
and our grandparents and our forefathers
وأجدادنا و أسلافنا
going on and on and on before that,
وبالاستمرار قبل ذلك
and I, no matter how romantic or how idealistic I am on this journey,
وانا بغض النظر عن الدرجة التي كنت بها عاطفياً اومثالياً آنذاك
I did not know that until two weeks ago.
لم اعرف ذلك حتى قبل أسبوعين مضوا
So what's this all about?
إذا ما كان ذلك كله؟
Well, there's an image I'd like to show you,
هنالك صورة أرغب بعرضها عليكم.
quite a special image, and it wasn't essentially the image I wanted to choose.
صورة مميزة بحق ولم تكن الصورة التي أردت اختيارها
I was sitting there the other day, and I have to finish on a strong image.
كنت جالساً ذلك اليوم وكان لا بد لي من إتهاء كلامي بصورة قوية.
And somebody said, "You have to show them the picture of the Nenets. The Nenets."
قال لي أحدهم: "يجب أن تريهم صورة النانيف. النانيف".
I was like, yeah, but that's not my favorite picture.
أبديت موافقتي بالرقم انها لم تكن المفضلة.
She went, "No no no no no no no. It's an amazing picture.
قالت لي: " لا. لا. لا. لا. لا. لا" أنها صورة رائعة.
You're in his eyes."
أنظر فأنت بعينيه".
I said, "What do you mean I'm in his eyes? It's a picture of the Nenets."
قلت:"ماذا تعنين بانني في عيونه؟" "إنها مجرد صورة لرجل النانيف".
She said, "No, look, look closely, you're in his eyes."
قالت لي:" لا. أنظر. تمعن. أنت داخل عينيه".
And when you look closely at this picture, there is a reflection of me in his eyes,
وعندما تمعنت أكثر بالصورة اكتشفت أن هناك انعكاساً لصورتي في عينيه
so I think perhaps he has my soul, and I'm in his soul,
لذلك ظننت لربما لديه روحي وأنا في روحه،
and whilst these pictures look at you, I ask you to look at them.
وبينما تنظر هذه الصور إليكم، انظروا اليها.
You may not be reflected in his eyes,
قد لا تنعكس صورتكم في عينيه،
but there is something extraordinarily important about these people.
لكن هناك شيئا مهماً حول هؤلاء الأشخاص.
I don't ultimately have the answers, as I've just shared with you,
لا املك حقاً الاجوبة ، انا شاركتكم الصور الاجوبة لذلك.
but you must do. There must be something there.
أنتم من ينبغي له ذلك. لا بد أن يكون هنالك شيء.
So if you can briefly reflect on what I was discussing
لذلك إذا تمعنتم قليلاً بما كنا نناقش
about beauty and about belonging and about our ancestors and our roots,
حول الجمال وحول الانتماء وحول أجدادنا وجذورنا كذلك
and I need you all to stand for me, please.
كل ما أحتاجه الآن ان تقفوا لي أرجوكم.
(Laughter)
(ضحكات)
Now you have no excuse. It's almost lunchtime,
لا عذر لي الآن. فقد حان وقت الغداء.
and this is not a standing ovation, so don't worry,
وهذه ليست بوقفة حفاوة فلا تقلقوا
I'm not fishing for compliments.
فأنا لا أتصيد المجاملات.
But you were given a compliment a few minutes ago.
فقد حظي كل منكم بمجاملة قبل قليل.
Now I want you to stand tall.
أريدكم الآن أن تقفوا جميعكم.
I want you to breathe in. This is what I say.
أريد ان التقط انفاسي. هذا ما سأقوله لكم.
I'm not going to get on my knees for two weeks.
لن أجثو على ركبتي لاٍسبوعين
I'm not going to ask you to carry a goat,
ولن اطلب منكم أن تحملوا ماعزاً
and I know you don't have any camels.
لإانا اعرف أنكم لا تملكون جمالأ.
Photography's extraordinarily powerful.
التصوير شي قويُ للغاية.
It's this language which we now all understand.
إنها لغة يفهمها الجميع.
We truly do all understand it,
جميعنا يفهمها حقاً.
and we have this global digital fireplace, don't we,
كلنا نملك تلك المدفأة الرقمية، أليس كذلك؟
but I want to share you with the world,
لكنني أريد مشاركتكم ذلك العالم
because you are also a tribe.
لأننا أيضاً قبيلة.
You are the TED tribe, yeah? But you have to remember that compliment.
أنتم تنتمون لقبيلة تيد، أليس كذلك؟ يجب حفظ تلك المجاملات في ذاكرتكم.
You have to stand tall, breathe in through your nose,
يجب ان تقفوا بشموخ. خذوا نفساً من انوفكم.
and I'm going to photograph you. Okay?
سألتقط لكم صورة. اتفقنا؟
I need to do a panoramic shot, so it's going to take a minute,
احتاج لأن تكون لقطة شاملة، ولذا ستأخد دقيقة واحدة.
so you have to concentrate, okay?
لا بد لكم ان تركزوا. اتفقنا؟
Breathe in, stand tall, no laughing. Shh, breathe through your nose.
تنفسوا. قفوا عالياً. لا أريد ضحكاً. صه، تنفسوا من أنوفكم.
I'm going to photograph.
سوف ألتقط الصورة.
(Clicks)
(طقطقات)
Thank you.
شكراً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)